Today is February 2nd, 2026.
My name is Caitlin Sheets and I'm currently in the Glasscock building, is that right?
In the basement.
I'm here with Lauren Huntley and we're conducting this interview on Texas A&M's campus and College Station.
The interview is part of an oral history project documenting the experiences of Aggies for the 150th celebration of Texas A&M.
Do I have your consent to record?
Yes.
Awesome.
Thank you so much.
So I'm here with Lauren Huntley, as I said, a former undergrad, currently a new grad student.
That's what I thought.
yes that's awesome um so thank you for joining me and sharing your story um thank you um can you give me a little bit of background like before you came to texas a&m yeah where you're born yeah so i was born in cincinnati um i come from rural ohio people and i still say pop yeah good stuff um there was a scary week there with the college playoffs
would have gone to Ohio State if we beat Miami, but alas, Carson Beck made that not an issue.
Yeah, so I always imagined I'd go back up to Ohio for school.
All my extended family is still up there.
My dad went to my university in Oxford, Ohio.
My mom went to Iowa State for a semester before going to cosmetology school.
So a lot of roots are in Ohio.
We moved down here 20 years ago this summer, which is crazy.
We went to Sugar Land, Missouri City area.
I was there in elementary school until 5th grade.
And then we moved to the Woodlands.
I was there 5th through...
You know, until I went to college.
Yeah, I have two siblings.
One's a twin sister who did not pursue higher ed at all.
And then my brother who went to A&M who kind of fed me the Kool-Aid.
Oh, is that where it came from?
Yes.
My sister and I visited him one weekend and I was like, this isn't so bad.
Yeah, sure.
And then after high school, I was encouraged slash you're going to do Lone Star Community College for a year.
I only had to do it a year instead of two to get my full associate since I graduated high school with like 27 college credits.
My high school is a very, very huge proponent for AP, dual credits.
Which high school?
Woodlands High School.
Woodlands?
Okay, that's awesome.
Yeah, we're 6A.
It's...
It's hard to explain, but everything's competition and the Woodlands.
That's stressful.
Yes, it is.
If you want to do varsity or be the lead in the, I did theater in high school.
So if you wanted to do leads, I was on the improv troupe in high school.
I was the president for two years and it was pretty much, you have to start doing that when you're five.
Wow.
Because it's a six day.
I graduated with 1100 kids.
So it's a different culture.
Yes, very much.
Yes, it's very competitive.
Academics and athletics equally.
I think that's kind of hard to find, but again, it's Texas.
So academics have always been present in your mind.
Yes.
I wouldn't say, though, I tried in high school.
English particularly became very, very easy to me.
I was always a really big reader as a kid.
I have an edition of Little House on the Prairie on my bookshelf.
That is a good example of why I am the way I am today.
The breadcrumbs are always, always there.
I originally was actually going to study English, but they recommended to transfer into A&M.
You already had your foreign language done, and I did not.
And so the BS of history here at A&M offers without the foreign language, and that was the only other major I was interested in, so I kind of naturally...
went in there I'm gonna say that might have been the first year they offered that so the timing was very very kismet and I'm very very thankful um and I was an English minor so it's still a big part of my life it's a big philosophy of my history training and all that but yeah yeah academics have always been a big part of me it's definitely been I was embarrassed to get these I was that kid in English who like if Lauren didn't read we're shrewd yeah math and science were always pretty hard for me I never really that's fair yeah I never really got that but
Was there like an English teacher professor that really encouraged you?
Yeah, I had a wonderful junior and senior.
So both of those were dual credits.
Dr. Heidi Bardenhagen was my junior.
And then Dr. No, he's not a doctor, sorry.
Jeff Murren was my senior.
And like he used to be the only teacher who taught senior year dual credits.
So it was like my brother had him when he taught at McCullough, the junior high school.
So then he moved to the high school.
He's just amazing.
He's tatted up and he's just awesome.
Dr. Barbara Hagan, obviously overqualified.
Just tried everything to make sure he knew the more analytical side of English and it's not just the curtains were blue which symbolizes sadness.
Yeah, but she was unfortunately ran out of the woodlands.
She was teaching lenses of English and one of them is a Marxist lens.
She was not saying she's a huge Marxist, but there is a kid who is part of the Turnpoint USA club.
He brought that to parents and she was alleviated of her duties.
That's wild.
I thought that's still happening.
Absolutely.
That was 2023.
2023 and it's still people, the Marxist is scary.
It's the most frustrating because she left academia because she said it focused too much on research and she just wanted to teach.
That's so rare.
And she could have gone to a private or a small liberal arts school, but she chose to credit English.
Yeah.
I really credit them too for, you know, like if I do defend successfully my PhD, like I would definitely make sure to knock on wood to find them and be like, you are a huge part of this.
That's great to hear.
I love it.
I love seeing where it comes from.
Oh yeah.
No, totally.
And like,
So I particularly focus on Native American history.
And I was torn between that or Holocaust studies, two very lighthearted areas of history.
But growing up, my parents' favorite movie, one of theirs, is Dancing with Wolves.
And obviously it's not historically the best.
But it was just always kind of in the background.
My parents are really big history fans, maybe not in the academic sense, but more just in popular culture or documentary.
My mom's a huge reader, so it's always been encouraged to, you know, listen to the real quote-unquote real story or give space for them.
Right, absolutely.
Can I ask if your parents are educated?
Yeah.
My father went to Miami University.
It is in Oxford, Ohio.
I almost went there.
I was accepted, but it was $30,000 for out of state.
Thanks.
But yeah, my dad, he majored in sports management, but now he is the VP of an all-in-one company for supply chain.
So just because you get a degree in something doesn't mean that's what you have to do.
And then my mom went to Ohio State for a semester before she went to cosmetology school.
So me being A&M,
graduating, very, very big deal.
My mom does not take this for granted and really instilled that in me and Rachel, my twin sister, to try to do something.
I was about to ask about your siblings too.
Yeah, that's the one thing that you really can't get taken away from you is that education and the skills you learn in the classroom.
That's very true.
So come from a very academic family or even seems like a hardworking type of family.
So did you ever feel a lot of pressure or have that type of...
No, I never felt like if I didn't bring home an A, I'd be grounded for a month.
It was more of just, don't be a dumbass.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
It's kind of expected.
It's just, you excel.
You know, I was never pressured to have an actual job in high school.
School was the job.
So it was just trying to never to quit on anything that you make a commitment.
You've got to do it.
That was as well as theater and improv.
Just give 110% to everything you do.
My mom's dad farmed for 40 years, so...
A hard worker.
Yeah.
Do you think that those traits have followed you through?
How do you see that in your...
I think just not taking it for granted.
I think sometimes you see kids on campus who college to them was never a question.
It's just something they have to do to check off the box and maybe they're not appreciating of like, this might be the one time in my life
where I just get to read something and talk about it and try to expand yourself as a human, as a scholar.
I think that's so, so, so special.
And I think, you know, it's maybe the first time in a lot of society's history where a majority of its populace are educated, literate, and trying to improve in that area.
Very good point.
Um...
So we talked a little bit about this, about where history came from, but what made you choose Native American history?
Yeah, I can tell you exactly.
So I was taking Native American history, a little survey course with Dr. Angela Hudson.
I was in M207, this building over here on campus.
It's the A in engineering.
For some reason, a lot of history seminars are there.
It's like a huge, you know, 400-person seminar room.
Oh, okay.
And...
I just remember sitting there one day and I'm like, this is what I want to do.
Um, obviously it's not a, I'm an outsider.
I am not indigenous culturally related.
I'm not enrolled in any federally recognized tribes or state recognized tribes.
Um,
But it makes you view America in maybe a different light, more honest, more truthful.
It's a harder light to look at it, but it makes you feel more connected to the land, its people, its cultures.
Yeah, and it's not typically the first thing, or maybe in bold when you read textbooks.
Maybe it's a little sigh, and then once you get to a trail of tears, it's never really brought up again.
And that's something I'm very passionate about, is bringing it into the main historical conversation.
Yeah, I mean.
That makes sense.
Yeah, and Dr. Hudson is now serving as my advisor.
Full circle.
It's full circle.
It was just a once-in-a-lifetime opportunity, really, really, really.
How did you, was the first time you met her was in that class?
Yes.
Okay.
Yes, but it's pretty, it's a bigger class, so I don't know if we ever got a lot on one-on-one time, and then that following semester, or so fall, no, spring of 23, yeah, spring of 23,
She was teaching her smaller 300-level class called Native Americans of the South.
And I took that as well.
And again, just completely fall in love with it.
I would consider myself a Southern historian.
And I actually met a future roommate there.
That's so cool.
Yeah, just has overflowed my cup in so many ways.
But that's when we definitely had a way closer intimate working relationship.
And then that summer...
I was graduating early in August.
So I'm class of 25, but graduated May.
No, August the 24th.
So I'm a full year old.
And I basically reached out to her and said, like, hey, I need a job.
Like, do you need someone to refill coffee?
Like, anything, anything, anything I'll do for you.
And she said, like, I was actually about to reach out to you.
I need a research assistant for a project.
And that's what kind of got me on board to do actual factual history and not just reading about it.
I was researching a group of Native Americans who were here between 1904 and 1911.
They were football players here before we officially integrated.
And it's, you know, transnational.
We're dealing with people from Oklahoma.
We have a Cheyenne individual.
They're from Carlisle, the boarding school in Carlisle, Pennsylvania.
And, yeah, it just completely transforms what you think of A&M when we realize who was actually here taking classes before maybe we were in that national.
Right, yeah.
Intention Spotlight?
Yeah.
So we worked on that research together for a year.
We presented a paper together at the Alliance for Texas History Conference in May of 25.
That was my first conference.
And then I basically told her, like, hey, I'm applying for a PhD.
Like, I really want to do this for a while.
I think this fills me.
Like, this is amazing.
So here we are.
I am finished with my first semester as of
Fall of 25.
And now we're entering spring 26.
Congratulations.
That's awesome.
Thank you.
Actually, can you go back and talk a little bit about the Native Americans that were here before?
Yeah.
Because I have no knowledge of this.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
So we found six in this time frame.
All of them but one are Choptop.
Okay.
Which we think there might be something there.
And the other one that I mentioned, Cheyenne, his name is Michael Valenti.
He is actually from someone who survived a wounded knee.
His mother survived him, didn't he?
And he actually went on to marry.
She's Alaskan native.
Her name is Cecilia Baranovich, and her dad was actually a Russian trapper mogul.
So, insane.
And Michael went on after being here at A&M.
He coached for Baylor.
He had an amazing career in the minor league baseball as well as professionals.
He was part of the Cincinnati Reds for a little bit, so that was...
As a Cincinnati native, that was fun.
And then we also have George Marlowe.
He was also Choctaw.
Oh gosh, we have Sig Flincham, James Flincham, nicknamed Sig, who we think is married during his time here, which is odd because where was his wedding staying?
Right.
So unfortunately, a lot more questions are not answered with these men because there's a lot of questions about if they're being paid or not.
Um...
Because we have records of Michael Valenti and Victor Kelly called Chalk as he's Choctaw.
Chalk Kelly being paid at Carlisle.
So it's kind of hard to imagine why they would leave there and come to Texas when they have absolutely no ties here.
What year is this?
I'm sorry.
It's between about 1904 to 1911.
And this is a football period in which we have the head coach of Charles Moran
uncle charlie okay yeah yeah yeah that's yes so this is the only other time where a and m stopped playing ut there was claims that he had professionals which might have been those carlisle native players if they're being paid um and basically they said we're not playing you until moran's gone and we didn't play them for three years that's wild um so yeah we have
A lot of evidence of them being involved in clubs.
Mm-hmm.
They were very active in Ross Volunteers, which is ironic, as Sol Ross is a proclaimed, quote-unquote, Indian killer, yet he has indigenous people probably honoring him and his memory and his impact at Texas A&M.
They are part of the Glee Club.
They are known as, quote, ladies' men.
Oh, okay.
With these white women in Bryan.
Mm-hmm.
So it raises questions of interracial relationships.
Right.
So yeah, it's very exciting.
It's probably what's going to be my master's thesis.
Yeah.
So yeah.
Thank you for sharing that.
That was like just a person for me personally, because I'm trying to put different pieces of this puzzle together from an outsider.
Yeah.
There's so many pieces that just don't make sense yet.
No.
And so there was a fire in 1912 that like did away with the old main building, which has all of our records of where they slept, which I need to know.
Yeah.
Just a lot of those records that unfortunately are lost that would
probably answer a lot of those questions.
Do you want me to...
I have over 2,000 oral histories from Aggies, their wives.
Do you want me to go through those and see what I... Also, you can have access to them.
I'll make sure you get that.
Because this...
I feel like a lot of this is brought up in some of them.
Yes, so Chuck Kelly and Mike Valenti are probably the two biggest successes in terms of their football career while they're here.
Um, they were nominated for like a Southwest all time.
Who would be the best team?
It's both of them.
Um, Richard Kelly went on to live in LA, um, after.
Um, he was a PE coach for like 50 years at Hollywood High School.
That's wild.
And then he actually was a technical advisor for one of Judy Garland's first films, Pigskin Parade.
Um, Texas State accidentally gets picked to play Yale.
Um,
in the championship, so they have to rally the troop, rally the men.
Yeah, I actually got in contact with his granddaughter, Linda.
So that was an amazing phone call.
That's awesome.
Yeah.
No, it really has changed.
You know, sometimes I think with the Southern schools, you think a very specific group of people were sitting at that table.
Right.
And I think constantly looking at, is that true?
We have records of women taking classes here.
Before.
Before the 20th century.
Yep.
And as well as Mexican-Americans.
Absolutely.
Mexican-Americans.
So many.
So many Central Americans.
We have so many ags from India.
Mm-hmm.
I mean, it's crazy, crazy, crazy.
And they're probably in these yearbooks.
Because the most interesting thing about my native ags, which I forgot to mention, never graduated until Bill Leftwich in 1954.
Odd.
So they're here.
Mm-hmm.
Interesting.
I wonder what that is.
I think that might have been there only taking a class or two.
Oh.
But then, this is at a time when the whole school is working on the core schedule.
are you doing all day what are you doing all right yeah because it's it's very strict very strict very strict yeah i mean there's in the yearbook of like what time breakfast is what time march is what time is everyone walking the fourth period like it's a very hell military school it 100 is so we just want to know did that cause animosity or could it not because dr kelly was awarded most popular cadet for superlatives in one of the yearbooks
Um, so these are very well-known people on campus.
Yeah.
So it is fascinating that there is no sign of them today.
Yeah, that's so interesting.
When arguably the beginnings of A&M football being commercially successful is this team.
Hmm.
That's a big mystery.
Yes, it is.
I see why you're interested in that.
I'm a football nut.
I really am.
I, obviously, the amount of money the school's invested into it, I think that's partly why I'm like, okay, well, if
there's some areas of the school that are not as funded but we're putting hundreds of million dollars into our coaching salaries and nil and our facilities i'm gonna i'm gonna check in um obviously there's a lot of literature on native sport obviously with jim thorpe and um you know carlisle football team completely transformed the game as we know it so
They're very, very interconnected.
Another side thing.
I think we just, not inherited, but we're now housing all of the old film reels from the football.
Do you?
Yep.
Okay.
Just making sure.
Oh my God.
Oh.
Because there's photos.
We have photos of them in these games sometimes.
And it's like just being able to pick them out.
Right.
Because only Victor Kelly, I'd say, is phenotypically someone you could appoint as indigenous.
So there's something to that.
Very much so.
And they're calling him Choctaw.
They are not hiding their nativeness.
In the yearbook, they hail, oh, he's from the new state of Oklahoma.
He does the corn dance.
He does the war whoops.
But it's fascinating.
The more they become integrated into campus, the less they comment on their nativeness.
That's interesting.
Uh-huh.
So we kind of question, like, is this Aggie, the binding force, is this able to trump racial lines?
That's strong, yeah.
Yeah, there's something to that.
It truly is.
This is also going to be a random side thing, but you brought up the Aggie spirit.
And I've heard so many different people say what it means to them.
What does that mean to you?
I would say, really and truly, just taking the harder path, if it's the right path.
I would say that is probably the Aggie way.
Like, why am I getting choked up?
My parents were at the airport the other day.
They didn't go to A&M, but they were wearing A&M merch.
And they saw a young mom, just alone, just kind of struggling.
We had a toddler crying and, like, another kind of pulling on our arm.
And she's obviously having a hard time.
And my mom just walks up to her and says, like, can I hold?
Do you need to go to the bathroom or something?
We can watch them.
And she said, like, we call you all our Aggies.
Of course.
So, you know, I know people make fun of it, a cult or whatever, but you can go anywhere, anywhere, anywhere, and you will find someone.
And that is just enough to share a meal or lend a helping hand.
And I think that is so, so, so important today.
That's so powerful.
Truly.
Yeah.
And I hear all these stories about people giving their senior rings.
Oh, yeah.
And then they see somebody else out in the wild with it, and they just instantly have that connection.
Yeah, yeah.
That's so fascinating to me because I've never really – this all is very new.
Oh, absolutely.
And so, like, coming in from the outside, that's just like – It is a whole new world, and part of it breaks my heart because I want to say out of, like, 12 of my cohort for grad school, maybe only two of us went to undergrad here.
Oh.
Mm-hmm.
So they don't love it like we do.
It doesn't maybe mean as much to them.
You know, they came here specifically for a professor or maybe the stipend was the most handsome or something like that.
So they didn't get to really experience all the charm that A&M has to offer.
So yeah, I do try to, you know, amp it up or say, like, you really should go to a football game.
When you're here, baseball's super fun.
From baseball, it's easier to get in and out.
And, you know, our women volleyball team just brought home our first national title.
And it's just very exciting.
Basketball's doing good.
I have no idea what that would look like.
Yeah.
Yeah, I mean, it's just a very, very exciting time.
Athletic.
Athletically.
Yeah, athletically.
So obviously you were interested in history and as an undergrad you came here, but what made you continue on as that?
Dr. Hudson.
Specifically?
Yes, Dr. Hudson.
Native studies is kind of a smaller area.
My husband's also getting his master's at A&M in engineering.
I joke A&M owns us, but we just bought a house here.
We're putting roots down.
We're guaranteed here for five years with my program.
It just makes the most sense.
He also works full-time, so I did not apply to anywhere else.
This is it?
Yes, and I only applied out of Lone Star Community College today.
Wow.
That's impressive.
People say don't do that.
A lot of people say do not do that for undergrad and graduate, but I knew.
If you love it, you love it.
I love it.
Yeah, I'll be an ag for, oh gosh, undergrad was three.
Yeah, I was eight years.
You're almost an old egg now.
Almost old egg.
It's funny to me that the Aggies that I've talked to, they didn't go here, but they came as a professor or something.
They feel like they can't claim being an Aggie.
And I'm like, you taught here for 25 years.
It makes me really sad.
It makes me sad because you're shaping these Aggies.
They're learning things.
what that Aggie spirit work ethic looks like through you and the rigor that you are demanding from them.
That's 110% part of it.
Absolutely.
Yeah, that upsets me.
Yeah, it's one of those things in the back of my head that makes me really sad that I hear.
No, I mean, yeah, I didn't go to Miami or Ohio State, but, you know, you feel that connection through family or through just being associated with it for time.
That makes sense.
I have no problem if you teach your routine.
Right, right.
Yeah.
Or, like, even I encourage my kids to get their ad hearing.
Yeah, exactly.
I know.
It's expensive.
You put in the work.
And it's a wonderful tradition that not every school honors.
I mean, we have one of the highest graduation rates.
Oh, I didn't know that.
Absolutely.
Okay, that makes sense.
Yes, absolutely.
I want to say we're in the 90s.
That's unheard of.
It's not 90s, 80s.
Yeah, that's unheard of.
That's unheard of.
Absolutely.
Like, I don't think I've literally heard of any other university like that.
No, because it is, it's a part.
If you say to someone, I went to A&M, and you don't see their ring, you ask, well, is it getting resized?
What's wrong?
Is there something wrong?
It's a part of it.
It's 110% part of it.
I mean, I have a paperweight.
Like, when Will, my husband, got his ironing, my brother got his ironing, and me, my mom, there's this Etsy cellar that makes, like, a wooden ornament of it with your ear.
Oh, that's really sweet.
Yeah, like, 100%.
Very much so.
Yeah.
So, your brother, what was his field?
Parks and Rec.
Wow.
Yeah.
Awesome.
We need people like this.
Yes, we put the and in A and M. We are not A or M. Yes.
park so he actually um just accepted a new job we're very excited for him he is an aquatics man
So he runs and pretty much makes sure that lifeguards are being trained properly.
The equipment is good.
Patrons are happy.
Pools are clean.
It's running smoothly.
That's what he does.
He did that for the Woodlands Township for 10 years.
He was there from 16 to Trumpet.
And now he's moved to San Antonio for that.
So he's doing 23 facilities, one year-round auditorium.
We could not be more excited for him.
That's awesome.
That's amazing.
So...
Dr. Hudson, what...
Okay, she also is Native American Studies as well, right?
Yes.
Okay.
So what is her teaching style?
Because I've never taken a class here, obviously, but... Yeah.
So I would definitely say she is trying to get you prepared for asking questions that you just have to approach every single text with, every single primary document with, and every single archive trip.
What am I asking?
Who wrote it?
Where do they go to school?
Who's their advisor?
It's all connected.
She really stresses that.
You know, what sources are they engaging in?
What secondary sources?
Who's she pushing back on?
Whose work are they building upon or who are they kind of disputing?
You know, when you go into an archive, it can be simple as take a picture of what you want and then write a little note to yourself because you're going to forget in two weeks why you took a photo of that.
She taught me try to be kind to your future forgetful self.
She says that sometimes, and I always try to remember that.
She's very primary-based.
That's so important.
In our 300-level class, she'd have a worksheet of, like, okay, pull out a line, explain the source they got this from.
Is this a good interpretation of the source?
You don't see that a lot in history classes at, like, those levels.
It's mainly, again, I think it's just a misconception of the history field in general of just regurgitating a timeline or something that we completely diverge from.
past 100 level class, especially here at A&M.
But yeah, she's a wonderful, wonderful person to learn how to dissect, look at that document in the context, how does that impact.
She also comes with an English background.
She has a master's in English as well.
So,
Reading.
Yeah, and that's what a lot of my personal statement was for the grad program.
I have a huge reading background.
I am a huge reader.
I read to work in over at the English department.
It was incredibly impactful to me.
Just meeting the source where it's at.
Right, yeah.
A hundred percent.
When you were undergrad, you said you were English, correct?
What professors there, what kind of skills were transferable to?
Yeah, so I...
It was an English minor, so I took, you know, the comp and rec at the dual credit level in high school.
So then when I got here, I took, oh gosh, a 19th century American novel with Ira Dworkin, who's fabulous, who wrote a rec letter for me.
I took Chaucer with Dr. Britt Mize, all in Middle English.
I read The Canterbury Tales, all in Middle English.
That was fantastic.
And then with Dr. Cooper, I took American novel World War II on.
And as far as Dr. Workman goes, again, just it's really easy to bring the 21st century with you when you're looking at stuff.
When you're reading Uncle Tom's Cabin.
Yeah.
When you're reading, you know, Squatter and the Dawn or something like that.
When you're reading Mark Twain, you want to make it accessible to you, but you just can't do it all the time.
And he would assign a healthy portion every night.
You'd come to class reading 100 pages each time, and that does prep you for grad school, but also just how can I read efficiently and effectively?
And then Brett Mize, he was wonderful, and the very first day of class, it's a 400-level Charleston class.
And...
he said something Middle English.
He goes to saying, this is how it would sound.
And I swear to you, I heard two kids drop right then and there.
Like, I cannot do this.
Right.
Oh my gosh.
I really, really stuck with me.
Just aspects of Chaucer.
You know, Pinterberry Towels.
It's literally a tale-telling contest on a very serious pilgrimage.
So it's just between, it's a balance between earnest and game.
okay and that is where I really rest how I approach a grad seminar when I'm answering questions because I think academia is very very stuffy and unacceptable and it is this wall and it doesn't have to be so I try to always manage the earnestness and gain and whatever I'm doing um and then that last English class I took
There's a wonderful book called Sex and the Cherry by Jeanette Winterson.
It's a post-modernist work, and it's just absurd, and it's awesome.
And I highly recommend it.
It's just good.
It's just good stuff, and there's no one universal truth, all that good stuff, post-nihilism.
You can get it from World War II.
Um, so how do you actually, um, on one hand, people say history is very one-way, linear, and then on the other hand, there is no one truth.
Yes.
How do you marry those two?
I'm allowed.
I am no one truth, especially if you're an indigenous person.
scholar like indigenous studies scholar like myself or if you focus on black history or Mexican-American history or any minority or marginalized history you are not the spotlight so that dominant narrative you can go but all day and I think you have to accept that frustration that you have to meet that middle and it's maybe the more uncomfortable version of
But trying to be respectful to both sides and not just painting one as the villain and one as the savior, that doesn't do anything good.
No.
That isn't honest.
Yeah.
So it's difficult and it's frustrating.
There's people in my cohort who roll their eyes.
at what I do, and it's fine.
Speaking more about that, the uncomfortableness in history, because there's facts and events that are uncomfortable, what would you tell people who are uncomfortable when they're learning these things?
That's wonderful.
It means you're human.
I am so glad that you can walk through the Holocaust Museum and go, that's horrific and tears.
That means you're human.
I think expecting entertainment from history.
Okay, go to the movies for that.
If you want to feel good about history, that's just propaganda.
Read a book for that.
Read a fiction book for that.
I just don't think history is necessarily the outlet for entertainment, for pleasure, for... You know, if you're interested in the sublime, read Lovecraft.
You know what I mean?
Yeah, that's a really good point.
It's just not, I think, something that needs...
a casual viewing.
I think it's a very serious, almost sacred thing.
That doesn't mean that only learned people or the highest of people get to touch it or interact with it.
I'm a huge proponent for public history, but I think it's the open-mindedness of knowing that there's a million truths to this one statement.
There's a million historians who write that sentence completely differently.
And that's beautiful.
I find that beautiful.
It's really encouraging, actually.
Yeah, they're like...
We were explaining this for a student that I was tanning for.
And she said, like, what do you mean when we say historians debate the date things happen?
And I said, okay, 9-11 always happened on September 11, 2001.
We're not debating that.
We're debating when did something start?
When did that movement end?
When did the war on terror end?
Who are the players involved?
That's what we're talking about.
So it's more of the nitty-gritty details of that broader narrative and that broader history and story that we are evading and trying to find a smoking gun primary document that blows open or completely refutes the common accepted story.
That's what I think that is.
So that's, again, once you get past that 100-level history class, you can start asking those questions.
But it's a good foundation.
At the end of the day, it is helpful to know
that do help you, but it's not the end of the deal.
That makes sense.
So someone from an outside in our political climate right now, looking at all the different rhetoric that's going on, what are your thoughts on...
So Texas A.M. is a land-grant university.
That means the Moral Act of 1863 granted these lands.
It comes from 183 tribal nations.
the mission of the land-grant university is equally agricultural mechanical also the humanities that is tangent that is twofold they live in tandem together that has always been the joint mission you cannot have one without the other for a wholehearted liberal education little l not big l location liberal education and today if you want to get
Specific with it, A&M doesn't stand for Agricultural Mechanical College of Texas anymore.
It's symbolic.
Rudder changed it to be symbolic.
We're honoring that past.
Today, I'm sure the most populated majors are ag and engineering.
That's fine.
But we're that and.
We're the ampersand.
You can't have one without the other.
It's a federal law that at Texas public universities, you have to take six credits of history.
Mm-hmm.
It makes a well-run education.
I think to be a informed voting participant in the body politic, you have to know a certain level of things to know what your freedoms are granted to you.
That's just something you can't escape from in any history class.
Um, so does the current global climate scary?
Yes.
I'm okay saying that.
Um, and
It hurts to know that Aggies are being turned away, being told they don't matter because of their academic desires and pursuits.
I think when we hear these certain buzzwords, a certain stereotype or character comes to mind.
And that's just not the case.
When you're sitting in these classrooms that are discussing these topics, you're not seeing the blue haired, angry woman.
I'm married.
I am dirty blonde.
You're just, I think it's easier to create an enemy instead of sitting at that table together and having a conversation and banning certain works, banning certain topics.
They do not erase them.
They only create a drive to seek them somewhere else.
And wouldn't you rather than be discussed at Texas A&M with Texas A&M professors?
That's a very good point.
Yeah, making knowledge forbidden is never... Never.
I don't think it's historically ever helped.
No, no.
You know, I try to look at what the Nazis did and try to maybe go the other way, but that's just me.
Yep, very true.
So these really hard conversations...
A lot of, a lot of outside forces are, they, they, they want to leave those conversations.
They just don't want to have them at all.
Um, from your, cause you, your history, you, you have all the, like, that's what the, you look back at history.
Yeah.
So like looking back at history, has that ever helped?
No.
Okay.
No, you're,
Creating ignorance that's only going to affect your voting class.
And also, most people who sit in the Senate today are history majors because they're all lawyers.
Okay.
So you're creating a dumber body.
If that's the point, you're doing an amazing job.
But then you are just degrading what it means to be an Aggie at the end of the day.
110%.
You're making my degree less aggressive.
in the thousands that came before me.
Thank you for sharing that.
I know that's hard.
No, I know it's hard, but I hope... Again, if it has to come from someone, I'd rather it look like someone that maybe the people encouraging these views can align with.
Very good point.
So...
What would you say to undergrads who are interested in going to grad school, pursuing a line that you, like you have, like following in your kind of footsteps?
Yes.
So I found it to be completely different.
Completely different than an undergrad.
It is, most of the time, at least in the history department, classes you meet once a week for three hours.
You're in a room with 12 people.
You are...
find people that are 110 percent of themselves all the time and they're such characters and that's part of it and you're just in these rooms with people that you never would have met elsewhere um and just being exposed to so many different worldviews or what they believe to be the truth or what is right i think it feeds your soul um
You know, I'm the first person in my family to pursue a higher graduate degree, so that's kind of scary.
It's a little isolating.
You know, I talk about what I have to do or what I have to read or, you know, what the next steps look like.
And there's a proudness there.
They love the name of me being in this program, but actual nitty-gritty details, I think maybe some of the lust, the luster wears off.
Yeah.
That's a very good point.
I never thought about that.
Yeah.
What do you do about that?
That feeling?
I like quite a ton.
Because a lot of times if you're supporting party members who are doing this, who are infringing upon academic freedom, your daughter complaining about it, no, that sucks.
What are you going to do?
Right.
Very true.
What are you going to do?
Because, again, then it becomes I'm a snooty academic.
I know more than you.
That's what the conversation becomes.
It becomes I'm being brainwashed and out of A&M.
Oh, yes.
The pinnacle of leftist propaganda takes A&M.
Okay.
Yeah.
There is that big disconnect between academia and the everyday, quote unquote, everyday people.
How do you think we should bridge this?
I know this is a very big, scary topic.
No, it is.
And I think it's, what are we assigning in our high schools?
Are we only assigning fiction works to connect our students to these?
Let's bust down a monograph.
Even if it's just reading the introduction.
I think so it's not so jarring when students are interacting with it in high school and expecting to speak eloquently for a grade on it.
I think that will leave some pressure.
I think modeling high school more like college campuses.
I'm very lucky the Woodlands High School had an hour and 30 classes.
You only met four classes a day every other day.
I think that's more realistic.
I think there's some high schools that are 50 minutes.
Wow.
you're going to die if you're in a Tuesday, Thursday, hour and 30 class.
You just will.
Yeah, I would definitely say, what are we teaching before we get here?
And maybe it's on historians.
How am I writing?
Am I just writing to appease my adversary at a New England school that I'm jealous of?
So I'm using these big words when I don't have to.
That's not saying you need to dumb down your writing.
I think making your writing accessible is something everyone should strive for.
Absolutely.
Very much so.
I'm thinking about also the older generation as well.
Because it seems like we're having conversations at each other and not...
Yes.
Yeah.
We're all having different conversations.
Absolutely.
Okay.
I'm sorry.
front of me.
I'm taking the chance to pick your mind about it.
What do we do about that?
If you want my honest to God answer, the world's going to look completely different when we word that out.
I'm not wishing death upon pandems.
I am not.
I have family that's in that generation.
I love them to death.
It's just a different world than they grew up in.
And it's a different world than I grew up in.
And that's okay.
That's just the passage of time.
That doesn't mean that what it means to be an American is any less, what it means to work hard is any less.
It's just, I think more now than ever, there's younger generations are okay with looking at something and saying that's wrong and saying that loudly.
And I think maybe part of it hurts to know that, you know, something might change and you won't reap the benefits of that.
You have to be the guinea pig that had to go through it when it was crappy.
There is a pain in that, and I completely, like, I completely get that.
Yeah, very much so.
Yeah, but I think a part of it definitely stems.
My grandpa, like I said, he farmed, and they were very intent on only having two kids to replace him and my grandma.
Oh.
That's a very, not Western thinking, I'd argue.
No, it's not.
Yeah.
Just making the world better when you left it.
And I don't think that's where we're at right now with older generations.
I think they're trying to extract the best they can while they're still here.
Maybe there is a fear in that.
But I also think, look at aging.
Look at the golden girls, how old they were when they started filming.
They were in their 40s and 50s.
today entertainment is different today attention spans are different today is different today i just think there's anger and not recognizing the world you grew up for died for fought for sacrificed for and i completely sympathize with that that's very valid yeah but again if there's always room to approve yeah yes yes absolutely
Yeah.
Personally, I find comfort in talking to professionals in their own field about the way the world is and where we're going.
So seeing that gives me hope.
Yes.
I think, you know, sometimes I have great responses and it doesn't give me hope.
Yeah.
Again, I'm meeting these kids in the very beginning of their academic journey most of the time.
I find that so exciting.
Mm-hmm.
So, like, that first response I just got for my TA class, I was doing line-by-line edits.
So I'm like, when's the last time?
Because this kid was probably in high school post-COVID.
Wow.
This kid probably never had a high school before COVID.
Right.
I would argue today, probably most teachers are teaching from an iPad.
They upload something to Canvas and say, have it done to me by the end of the day.
Wow.
Most likely.
I didn't know that.
Yeah, that's the thing.
I haven't been in high school in so long.
But, I mean, today we're teaching for test grades, standardized test grades for fun day.
We're not teaching them how to phonetically talk anymore.
There's a literary crisis in elementary schools.
Kids don't know where they live.
Kids don't know their parents' names.
Their numbers, too.
They don't know phone numbers.
Yeah.
It's a question of are we teaching our kids to check off a box or
or Haitian kids to be critically thinking adults in the real world.
That's okay.
Yeah, that's fine.
Well, done more.
That's fine.
So, you're a TA now, or are you actually fully teaching a class, or are you just...
I'm just a TA right now, so you have an option to be a gal, which is a graduate lecturer, when you are done, I want to say, with all your coursework as a PhD student.
That's exciting.
And you get additional funding for that.
Yep.
It's really exciting.
Exciting and scary, considering what I would teach.
True.
It's a very hard topic.
Yeah, it's not entirely like my parents.
I'm like, why?
You know?
For some reason, Native American history is okay to them.
Oh.
Yeah, they don't.
My family does not see the powder that I do that Native American history is on the top of the wall.
Not now, not tomorrow, but it will be.
At 110%.
Yeah.
Because it's not going to be narrative.
It's not going to be narrative.
It's looking at the federal government and saying, they killed 300 people at Sand Creek.
Yeah.
It wasn't a battle.
It was a massacre.
Yeah.
And that's not comfortable.
It's not comfortable.
Not comfortable.
Yeah.
I had this conversation, almost exactly this conversation, with some of my old cohort when I was in grad school, because I was in my very last year, and they cut our program.
And...
We were having this conversation with the anthropology kids, how they didn't want us to make noise on the way out because they were scared they're going to be the next.
And I was like, you're already on the chopping block.
Yeah.
You're already.
They're already there.
You're already there.
Because I was folk studies, and it's inside of anthropology.
Got it.
So.
Yeah.
They're trimming the fat.
They're testing the waters.
Testing the waters.
Hmm, so I hope... Spot fog boiling situation.
Yeah, I hope women in gender studies as loud as humanly possible.
I hope these tenured professors are as loud as humanly possible.
Absolutely.
Even if it doesn't change anything for them, for the next people.
Wait, wake up!
You think Parks and Rec at Texas A&M is filling chairs?
Right.
No.
That's a very good point.
There's so many majors here that I'm wondering.
Oh, my gosh.
Sports management?
Exactly.
Like my dad?
We tried to have a journalism boot.
Reboot.
We saw that went.
Actually, I don't know much about that.
Oh.
This is some lore.
This is some old lore.
Basically, under, before Welsh, we had a president.
Kathy Banks said her name.
I've heard her name before.
Yes.
She falls over the carpet.
do the journalism department here at AM because I think it's telemarketing telecommunications and journalism is under the same department here at AM I think they pretty much want to compete with UT because UT has a very prolific journalism department and they were going to bring in a tenured professor from UT to completely redo this it's coming together yeah yeah
It comes out that it went from being, you're going to keep your tenure to tenure track to visiting the lecture.
Like, it just kept winding down and winding down.
And then a group chat was leaked.
Yeah.
There's comments about the professor's race, her political affiliations, and how that is never going to stand at Texas A&M.
Kathy Banks is loved.
And then Mark Walsh.
Yeah.
That happened just... Oh, yeah.
Oh, yeah.
What was that, 23?
23, 24?
That's even sooner than I thought.
I was taking...
I just think I remember us taking a summer film and English cross-listed class with Dr. Francis?
Yeah.
It was wonderful.
Right.
Yeah, it was a great class, but in the middle of it, this was coming out.
And being on campus during that was fascinating.
What was the general vibe?
In the English department, because I've only seen this through the English department during that class, and Dr. Francis is a black man.
That doesn't feel good.
He tried to make it lighthearted and joke, and students would talk about it before class and say, that's awful.
But I never got the rundown on how many were taking that just to get an English credit done.
I don't know.
Students were like, that's awful.
Nothing came out of it, though.
It's really sad.
No, and, like, Kathy Banks, like, got at the library.
Yep.
Like, Dr. Francis was, like, asking if, like, hey, can y'all rent this movie for me?
And I was like, hmm, look about it.
And I was like, no, like, I'm showing it in class tomorrow.
Like, I didn't need this remorse.
No, but I think, again, it's just trying to find excuses because that's the enemy.
It's that woke leftist ideology that would infiltrate, quote-unquote, infiltrate Texas A&M.
indoctrinated our students, our children, that's always the thing, indoctrinated our children, even though most of the people talking about this do not have students at Texas A&M.
Right.
And they're grown ass adults, most of which did not go to college.
You do not have any skin in this game.
You have none whatsoever.
The average American does not read more than one book a year.
Yeah.
So who are y'all mad at?
Right.
Who are y'all mad at?
No.
So the frustration is just compounded.
Yes, yes.
I'd say I think Mark Welsh was kind of turning the new page, turning the new leaf.
I think he was making wonderful changes, like taking a poll online.
He was talking about decreasing admissions the next five years to kind of combat the congestion that we feel in College Station and Bryan.
I think these were lovely, real conversations to be having.
My question is, he's a retired...
So something starry general.
If he's not Texas A&M material, who is?
Who do you want?
Right.
Because picture perfect.
It's picture perfect.
Picture perfect.
So.
Because remember, he left because Republican lawmakers were giving him shit on Twitter.
Saying you didn't do something fast enough.
When he stand by his professors and educators.
Because he acknowledged, hey, I don't have a degree in English Lit.
I'm going to let her decide what's appropriate.
And that's 100% what the average boss does is acknowledging when it's not my profession.
It's just not what I know the most about.
Deferring to.
It's a level of humility that I admired so deeply in him.
And to see that get punished.
That is sad.
Yes.
Heartbreaking.
No, and it's been boiling.
And, you know, I kept checking every day on howdy during winter break to see if my sex and gender class was being canceled, edited, removed, what have you.
And I just kept checking it.
And, okay, I'll show up first week of class.
Okay, I'm going to show up second week of class.
We'll see.
How are you living with those emotions surrounding that?
I've been hearing it mainly internally.
I have not posted anything on social media.
Because again, then I'm a target and the history department's a target.
I'm an employee of Texas A&M.
I'm not protected by tenure.
And it's been proven that doesn't help you.
There's nothing protecting me.
And that is incredibly scary.
And again, I'm not the angry, bra-burning feminist that they think is taking these classes.
Mm-hmm.
I'm taking these classes because indigenous peoples have different ideas of what being a woman and being a man is.
Simple as that.
Even if you were.
And even if I was, who cares?
I'm giving A&M money.
Yeah, even if you were.
Even if I were.
What's it to you?
Who's it to you?
Who's the government saying what I can and can't read?
I'm yelling, I'm sorry.
No, no, that's fine.
Yeah, it's incredibly frustrating because it's such a slippery slope.
can and can't be taught what i can and can't read there's a definition of government overreach from the so-and-so small government party that's what's infuriating yeah like yeah yeah it's yeah and to make this decision as an interim president shame on you shame on you yeah
I don't think people realize, or maybe they do and they just don't care, that there's people behind these choices.
Not just making the choices, but the effect.
That people are out of a job.
They can't feed their family now.
Americans are out of jobs.
They can't feed their family.
Especially in this market, this job market.
And not only that, is the students that would take those classes...
signed up they were curious they wanted to learn something they they said they were told no you can't you can't be curious i know i'm supposed to be asking questions but no but i'm glad no it's just it's infuriating but i do have hope i see on facebook comments so many people are angry about this
So many people are angry about this, and that makes me so happy.
Yeah.
That it is not just people on campus.
After I just said, you know, if you don't have skin in this game, who cares?
Right.
And I completely don't want jobs to be critical.
But people are mad.
People are saying this is not my A&M.
I'm embarrassed to be an Aggie.
It's the same conversations OU was having a couple months ago.
Because it's antithetical to the idea of being an Aggie.
Yes.
You're not respecting.
Not respecting.
No integrity.
Yeah.
What is that?
We might have differences, but you come together, discuss it respectfully.
I think that is what an Aggie is literally bred to do when you're here.
That was one of the first things I learned was when I was reading the history that you might have differences, but you respect each other and you talk about it.
Yeah, because that happens even in, I'm sure, so many ag classrooms.
Well, I think we should breed this heifer on this day.
Well, I think we should do it this day.
That's a completely different, we're not talking about literature.
We're talking about something concrete, real that we can touch and feel.
But we're still having a disagreement.
And we have to have a civil conversation about how to remedy that.
And that's what you're taking away.
Very much so.
Yeah.
How does this, I think I know the answer, but how does this make you feel about the future of this university?
It depends on if Abbott's re-elected, if I can be completely honest with you.
It entirely hinges upon Abbott being re-elected because with his new foreign visa ban he wants to implement, that's going to impact us, that's going to impact UC, it's going to impact thousands of students.
It is an honor that someone in Taiwan wants to leave their family and come here when it's 80 degrees on Christmas and humidity's 100%.
That's an honor.
Yeah.
That's the anti-spirit.
This is the American dream.
100% signature.
And you are robbing that of thousands, thousands of people.
Truly.
And their families.
And it breaks my heart to know that we might lose an R1 distinction, which is the pinnacle of academic success.
We spend, I think, close to a billion dollars in research a year.
More than that.
Yeah, more than that.
Just put food on my table.
Mm-hmm.
keeps my lights on, you're impacting thousands of Americans with these decisions.
And soon-to-be Americans, too.
It's turning away people who want to be American, want to be Texans, want to be Aggies.
Yes, absolutely, 100%.
So that's what I'm more worried about.
The second we lose that R1, we lose professors, we lose grad students.
I've been jokingly encouraged to think about other places.
There's something with jokes, though.
Yeah.
I think it's heartbreaking.
And something needs to change.
At a state level.
I, to the eye, go blue in the face.
This is not a university level.
This is a state level decision.
There's been six flags over Texas.
So we are not a homogenous people.
I don't know where y'all got that idea from.
you go through an HEB, how many lines of other countries are you seeing that you can shop from?
Yep.
So.
Oh, that's very valid.
Yep, yep, yep.
Thank you for sharing those things in your heart.
Difficult.
Yeah.
How's the general...
I know I keep saying vibes, but how's the general atmosphere over here in this department and history?
We're terrific.
We're hopeful, though.
It is the best of times and the worst of times, really and truly.
We are so excited.
We're hiring three new faculty this year.
So obviously there's still interest.
There's still attractiveness to be at A&M, and we don't take that for granted.
We just sent out our acceptance letters for the new cohort for grad students.
That's so exciting.
That's really exciting.
So it is this very bittersweet time where we keep looking over our shoulders.
What would help this department and also just the faculty and staff here in general?
Trust, feeling like we are trusted to do our job that we were hired to do, that we were accepted to do.
Go away with the syllabus review.
I completely understand wanting to update course descriptions.
Some of those are 50 years old.
But you're hiring someone who's an expert in a field you might know nothing about.
I would trust them any day to say what's appropriate or not to teach.
Very fair.
Yeah.
I would say that.
Or have a literal statement saying that
We're not touching anything else.
We're good.
And this should have been done before the semester started.
Yeah, very much.
Was it two weeks they gave people?
Two weeks?
That's not enough time.
No, right before Christmas?
Not enough time.
Are you kidding?
People don't check their email.
No.
Sorry, that's me in a tangent.
No, no.
Yeah, people don't touch their emails.
No, it's complete.
No.
Yeah.
Again, you have to ask this question.
Are we a business or are we a school?
No.
Yeah, let the school be a school.
Yeah.
The people who say, what would you say to people who are, that have that fear of, they actually legitimately have that fear of, you're going to indoctrinate my kids.
What would you say to them?
They've been living at your house for 20 years.
You have to trust that the morals you raise them with are going to withstand.
And I think it is wonderful that they're being questioned.
And they might come out the other end stronger in the beliefs that you taught them.
110%.
That is a real possibility.
That's a really good point.
Yeah.
If you're nervous about a 16-week course completely transforming your child into an unrecognizable person, I think you need to have lunch with your kid.
Are you talking to your student weekly?
Are you checking in on them?
Are you just sending them Venmo's?
Damn.
Are you having a real relationship with your child?
What's more important to you?
My dad said he'd rather I come home pregnant than a liberal when I went to college.
That's rough.
Yes.
That's actually really upsetting.
What's more important to you?
How your child votes?
Or how they love and respect and treat others?
So...
And I get it.
I get the idea of sending your kid off.
I mean, I find it funny that people, you know, from other states come here because I'm like, how'd you hear about us?
I really get it.
You're sending your kid.
It's scary.
Thousands of miles away, hours away.
Hell, if you're in El Paso, you're not seeing your kid until Christmas.
So I completely get that.
It's just up to you to still engage because raising a child is not done once they hit 18.
Yeah.
That relationship doesn't dissolve just because they're in class.
Right.
So ask yourself, what's more important?
Maintain that relationship.
Have room in your mind and heart to be challenged yourself.
We're not saying you're wrong, you're a horrible person, you're a burning hell.
No one's saying that.
Difficult conversations are wonderful to have and you will come out stronger together.
I promise you.
That's very good.
That's a very good point.
Thank you.
It's a very good point.
It's...
I think parents right now are just...
There's anxieties in the country as a whole, and they're just... What is the closest thing that resembles that right now?
What is something that I can mirror, put that on?
And I think that right now is the conversation that's closest to home for parents.
I think that's all that is.
That's right.
Yeah.
I'm not a parent, so... Me neither.
Like, I can't...
But...
I think that's something that no matter what side you're on, that you really need to, even if things make you uncomfortable, as you said, to engage with these things and to understand that being uncomfortable, we're not attacking, no one's attacking you.
No one's attacking you.
You know, students, if you are feeling that, you know, if your parents ask you what you're reading and you know they're not going to like something, talk it through with them.
Mm-hmm.
Point to things that you did like, things that you didn't like.
If you say, I completely disagreed with that entire book, move on.
That's 100% okay.
I've read books and I'm like, the argument didn't sell me.
That's okay.
It can really be as simple as that.
It really can be.
It doesn't have to be, I have to email the person who wrote this, demand, they lose their job.
Like, no, it's not that deep.
It's pretty good.
I think also that
people are equating what professors are teaching with what they personally believe and those two things aren't the same no like it kind of it frustrates me that this actually became the word and the language that university implemented when doing the syllabus reviews but I on the current record I said like educating someone is not advocating so then I kind of bit my tongue when that became the slogan of saying are you advocating
For these ideologies.
That's so vague.
And they did that on purpose.
It's easier to just brush everything under a rug and throw it away and light it on fire.
That's 100% easier.
How do you know if it's advocating?
Right.
Are you wearing a pride flag?
Like, what does that look like?
Yeah.
It's just this vague monster that they can constantly change.
The oogie boogie.
Yeah.
So that's the scariness of it.
It can constantly change what they are attacking.
And I think that's what every department needs to be scared of.
Every single department needs to be scared of.
Every department.
Okay, if one department's on the chopping block, everybody is.
Yes.
And I'm not saying complete gut.
Yeah.
I'm saying professors.
Right.
Your citizenship status.
If you're married to the same sex.
Because they are saying one thing with this.
The public is personal.
And the personal is public.
That's 110% what it is.
So, it's just McCarthyism.
It's neo-McCarthyism.
That's all it is.
I've literally been saying that.
McCarthyism never went away.
It just changed.
I'm glad that I got to talk to you.
It's good seeing...
that okay this is going to sound really bad but it's good to see that we're we're not the only ones that are scared absolutely all of us are yeah i'd be more concerned if you pulled a kid over like you know you're waiting for the bus the shuttles and they have no idea what's going on that's concerning that's way worse in my opinion than being like i'm 110 for this i'd rather you be 110 for this and having no idea what's going on because that means you're actually reading informed yeah being informed yep
And that's one of the things that this university is supposed to do is make it informed citizens.
Yep.
That's part of the land grant mission.
Exactly.
Informed citizens.
So, um, not that I, I, it is, it, it is very like we're both, we're same hat.
We both have, we're both, it's, it's, it's comforting and also very sad that that's happening.
Um,
And this directly, obviously, affects you because you're teaching your TA.
Yes.
So how did you, whenever you got that news, what was the things that were going through your head?
I was heartbroken.
I still am.
I am heartbroken.
I did a guest lecture in the last semester about the 60s and 70s, and I was going to do actual social history on it.
I had slides I was making.
And I had a photo of Marsha P. Johnson, and I thought, I can't.
I can't.
So I just did pop culture in the 60s and 70s, and I slipped some stuff in.
I was like, hey, look, the Beatles have long hair now.
But then Mia Farrow, Marsbury's baby, has short hair.
What's that?
So I tried to make it accessible in ways that they can see concretely.
I think that was how I really tried.
I tried to do that, and...
I think another thing I strongly believe is that people who are against teaching about gender don't realize that the fact of even in their binary, to teach a binary, you're still teaching gender.
You can't teach about anything.
Yeah.
You can't teach about heteronormative marriage.
Nothing.
And that, I can't mention I'm married to a man.
That's upsetting.
That's...
The Aggie that I met here on campus that is a master's engineering student.
An exemplary Aggie.
I can't mention that.
You can't talk about your... That's because that's part of you.
That's part of me.
So...
That feeling of having to leave parts of you behind.
Parts of you behind.
And if you want to get technical, okay, you're telling a university that didn't let me accept women until 66.
They're getting rid of women's studies.
Even though A&M is mostly women today.
Oh, I didn't know that either.
There's more women in college than men right now.
I think that's scaring some people.
I would say yes.
Yeah.
How much time do you generally would put into creating those lessons?
Oh my gosh.
Three hours at least.
That's a lot.
Because it's making slides, making sure they're accessible slides.
It's double-checking my sources.
It's so much.
And that's per lesson.
Yeah, that's per lesson.
And I only did that one guest lecture.
But, you know, they encourage...
new profs to pretty much like over the summer write all your lectures so you can just hit the ground running and not have to play catch up and you can do an honest job on it and not just freak out right and I leaned on other grad students and said hey what do you have during this time period that I should probably mention too um yeah yeah yeah so to see that
You are encouraged to make it before, and you put so much time into it.
So to receive those emails of... To delete it.
Exactly.
Slap in the face.
It's a slap in the face.
I'm sorry.
No, I mean, just everyone has a gender.
Everyone has sexual orientation.
Everyone has a race.
Everyone has an ethnic, racial belonging.
These are all things you fail on the SAT.
Right.
It's okay.
It doesn't have to separate.
That's the whole point of why we're talking about it.
So we can have a more cohesive and new bio today.
So I think that's the most embarrassing thing.
And I think the line they were saying is they didn't want white kids to feel guilty.
That's, yeah, that was brought up a lot.
Unless your last name is Lee and you're related to Robert E. Mm-hmm.
How would you know?
Unless your mom's a united daughter of confederacy.
Also even then.
It's one of those things of, like, the sins of our fathers.
And if you're so far gone, I don't think you're feeling bad sitting in class.
That's my thing.
If you are so on that spectrum, I don't think you're feeling bad.
No.
You're looking at that through nostalgia.
You're not.
No, I think...
That pisses me off.
And I'm not just saying that as a northerner.
Like, what do you mean you feel guilty?
Yeah.
You didn't do it.
You should be disgusted in your country and try to have a better tomorrow that actually fulfills the Constitution.
Mm-hmm.
That's why I kind of brought up those hard, like, how would you address those hard conversations and those uncomfortable.
Yeah.
Because I think people also equate having those hard conversations where they're uncomfortable with needing to feel guilty.
Those things don't need to happen.
You can feel guilty as an American of I'm in the South that was built on the economy of this chattel slavery empire that we were.
How are we addressing that today?
It does not have to be shameful.
It does not have to be with guilt.
If we're approaching it with honesty, honestly trying to make the tomorrow better, I think that's beautiful and wonderful.
So that whole child guilt thing, how do you measure that?
Hey, raise your hand if you feel guilty.
Okay, still 1 to 10.
Yeah.
How do you actually do that?
Again, it's this elusiveness that means nothing.
Don't give them an idea.
It's this elusiveness that you cannot completely implement in the classroom.
Yeah.
Oh.
Yeah, that's not something like, it's not on the end of year or end of semester surveys.
No.
Yeah.
Like I said, the uncomfortable means you're human.
I'm glad you're feeling something.
If you're not feeling anything, learning about these horrific events.
That'd be weird.
You're weird.
Like, that's weird.
It truly would be weird if you didn't.
Yeah.
So, it's my two cents.
I think it's valuable because as a historian, you see that what's happened and the patterns.
Yeah.
The patterns are scary right now.
Yeah, you're right.
Yeah.
Because that's the first day of every history class.
It's like, why do we study history?
And without fail, a kid will raise their hand and say, so we don't repeat it.
And you just want to roll your eyes.
History doesn't repeat.
It rhymes.
It's not like an exact copy.
Right.
So, but you know, happy that he rose his hand.
Hey, that's something.
Something, yeah.
Something.
So, going to something a little lighter.
Yeah.
What is your favorite part about teaching and about even just studying history?
What's your favorite parts about it?
I was surprised by how much I enjoyed my guest lecture.
I improvised some of it, and, you know, getting back to my theatrical roots is always fulfilling.
Just seeing...
The spark, the connection, the faces change when they're understanding something.
That's priceless.
That is utterly priceless.
And they walk out and go like, that was my favorite lecture.
That's so special.
In terms of just loving history, I think just because it's everywhere.
If you're more connected, your country, your people...
You feel less alone, I think, because you know that people have been feeling similarly since human existence.
Like when you're reading Chaucer and there's a line about jealousy or sadness or rage, I'm okay because someone in 1394 felt that.
So I'm going to get through this.
So yeah, it's just the human condition I think is very, very comforting.
it truly is that's what i was like yeah yeah yeah even through time yeah we can find comfort in that we find comfort in that the people have always been people truly and like that way is yeah also amazing way but love is just everywhere really and truly without being really corny no it yeah love is really really everywhere and that that's probably the best part that's really touching
Um, so did you want to be a lecturer or do you want to continue to be a researcher?
What's the... That's something I've been grappling with that I hope I can answer more concretely probably by the time I'm ending PhD.
I think it was easy to do that pop culture lecture because like the stakes were lower.
Me talking about best picture winners versus having to explain, you know, Indian removal.
I feel a lot of weight in the ladder.
That feels very, very heavy responsibility-wise because I acknowledge completely that might be the only time people hear about it.
Yeah.
Not watch it.
Right.
In, you know, Dances of the Wolves.
But truly learns about it.
So that's very daunting.
Obviously, research is fun, you know, getting unique,
answers and filling in gaps where people may have never thought about and getting a fuller picture that's always wonderful um but yeah I really really enjoy teaching so we'll see yeah yeah but I think A&M does a wonderful job even though it isn't R1 it encourages actual education
It's not just someone reading off slides.
They encourage that connection, I think.
Very much.
So whenever you personally are learning and doing your research, and you have those really heavy topics, and you have that sinking feeling that you're talking about, how do you cope?
What are your coping mechanisms?
It's silly, maybe, but I wrote a paper on pretty much the legacy of Carlisle.
for one of my historiography classes last semester.
And I ended it with, it failed.
At the end of the day, Carmile failed.
And I think of myself a lot.
There's 572 federally recognized tribes in the U.S.
So every law, every broken treaty, they fail because they're still indigenous people today.
And there are modern people.
They're not stuck in the past.
Right.
I don't think that's silly at all.
I think, I think even if you said them a silly thing, I don't think it's silly to have those coping mechanisms.
So I'm just, I'm always interested in how other people.
Yeah.
Or, um, I'm not wearing it today, but you know, I have a turquoise ring and I have a silver bangle that's in Navajo and it's just, you know, these are tangible.
Right.
That, you know, indigenous hands made.
And there is something that, yes, they have to do that because they're in impoverished communities and
are majority indigenous, but, um, that beauty and that tradition is still with us today and is tangible.
So I would just say reminding that even though I am studying the horrors of the past, I still see the love of today very much alive.
Yeah.
That's a really good answer.
Um, cause that's another thing, like in my line of work, I hear the most horrific things.
Yeah.
Um, so yeah, like sometimes I take people's, I take people up on those things and I like, maybe I should try that.
No, yeah.
I think it's early, even today I'm reading a book on memorials for my, um, I'm doing an internship with the journal Texas history.
Oh, cool.
Um, and it's a public history facing, uh, publication.
And for my internship, I have to obviously read.
I can't just show up.
Um, and the book's called Memorial Media and they're covering, um,
you know, Columbine.
Oh, God.
Yeah.
God's happy as hell.
Mm-hmm.
Happy as hell.
Yeah.
So, you know, if it's just playing with my dog or listening to fun music, cooking dinner, like, I think it's just reconnecting with what you love today.
Very much so.
Yeah.
It's very human.
Very.
Because, again, human condition.
Yeah.
Human condition.
And it always has been.
Always, always.
Yeah.
There is something, as you said, there is something super comforting to see that people experience those things and they got through it or they did something to get, you know.
Whether we like it or not, we're going to get through it.
This too shall pass, whether you like it or not.
Yeah, truly.
So what are some of the fun things about being a graduate student?
Oh, it's this basement.
It sounds.
But the people, I, like, um, Meg McClure, Megan McClure, she's a fellow undergrad.
She's who I always wanted to meet in undergrad.
Like, friend-wise.
Like, just amazing.
Just completely same sense of humor.
Like, we are killing it.
We're the only two girls in our cohort.
So it's immediate, like, this.
Right.
Um, I would just say it's the people I've met really and truly.
And it's, it's a side of college.
You have never really thought about being in the undergrad.
It's getting the nitty gritty.
It's fun to not be the one sitting down, but standing up, I think.
Um, it's just getting a different perspective of the university experience, which is really, really exciting.
That's awesome.
Yeah.
How was, how was that experience of being a woman, um,
being one of the only two women has do you like you feel it you feel you feel it sometimes um like it feels like the guys just want to talk about iraq all the time and it's like i don't have anything in iraq um you feel it sometimes i think it doesn't help that both of us are social historians that maybe are not as seen as prestigious compared to military history yeah it
Yeah, it seems like the history field has dominated by specific parts of it, dominated by men.
Yeah, absolutely.
Yeah.
That's fine.
Right.
But, you know, historically, who was allowed to learn how to read?
But... Yep.
That's another thing.
You want to look at frustrations today?
Okay, well, we can probably give you a short joke answer for why that is.
But...
I think...
It's exciting to know that, you know, we're all in this together and we're going to get through it.
And it's good to have that little pact.
Right.
That ally.
I'd probably say that.
Yeah.
That makes sense.
I try not to think about, you know, us versus them.
That's not true.
Right.
It's not a competition.
It's not.
You just, you feel it when there's one guy...
who is, you know, two other guys could agree with each other.
I would say similar things.
But if Megan and I agree with each other, he'll go like, well, as the ladies have already said, that he would not do that for, you know, or as, you know, John Gabbo's already said.
He would never do that.
He would just say, well, as the ladies have already said.
And it's like, actually no one was thinking about my sex, but okay, thank you.
Right.
So yeah.
So even if you don't want to think about it, it's still brought up.
Yeah.
So if they see me as that, okay.
Right.
And maybe it's because I'm not ineligible, whatever.
There's an element to that.
I didn't think about that.
Yeah.
Yeah, there's nothing there for you other than maybe companionship, tonically, but...
Right.
Yeah.
I didn't even know.
That's a really good point.
That's a really good point there.
And gender dynamics and...
Um, workspaces too is really, always really interested me.
Yeah.
And it's, you know, our department head is Dr. Hudson.
She's a woman.
She's made it very clear that anyone preying on that, us women down here are not going to be handled.
So I'm under the rug whatsoever.
And that's very comforting.
That's really good to know that you have, if someone has your back.
Yeah.
I also didn't realize I'm so out of it.
I was like, oh yeah, she is the head of the department.
Yeah, she is.
She's full of that.
Wow.
Okay.
Old egg.
Yeah.
She went to Auburn, Georgia.
Wow.
Okay, I see why.
I see why.
That makes sense.
This makes a lot of sense.
It's all coming together.
No, it's just so fascinating to me that also when
how women experience position different positions too like like i'm sure her experience is so much so different from like 19 years ago to now oh yeah oh yeah oh yeah and you know i think a lot of it is also the aspect that we're in a smaller subfield indigenous studies really didn't come to be a respected right renowned maybe until the 80s or 90s and even then we're still fighting for space so
Yeah, still.
Yeah, I would probably argue maybe my peers see me less because of that, not because of my sex.
Oh, okay.
I'd say that.
It's, hmm.
So what is the, you said Iraq, so are most of the other people here military?
We have military, in my cohort specifically.
We have military, he's active in the Marine Corps.
That's interesting.
Yeah, the government's paying for him to be here.
I don't know.
And then we have a diplomat history.
And then we have another social... We have a guy working in the Philippines in World War II with, like, POWs.
And another social historian.
So, yeah.
It's mainly just the ones who are allowed us out are diplomatic in our military.
Who the latter has been
No, the diplomatic is very loud about not valuing social history as... That's actually just rude.
Yeah.
Yeah, but then he wrote a paper about the social history of World War 12, or 1812, and we were like, why did you choose a heart?
That's weird.
Yeah.
That's interesting.
I try to limit my time with him.
Yeah, that's fair.
Yeah.
No, I'd say we're all doing different things.
I'd say there's not a lot of...
There's almost no overlap between anyone doing any topic.
That's kind of good, though, because no one steps on each other's feet.
It's wonderful.
There's only one other indigenous guy, and he's doing his PhD.
Oh, okay.
And he's at Colonial Times, so we're not at the...
Complete... No, I'm Jen Crowe.
He's Colonial.
Okay.
Very different.
Yeah.
Yeah, because I know...
Researchers can also be, like, super territorial over things, too.
Which is also, like, that also happens in the library and curators.
Curators get very territorial over their collections and stuff.
They're like, it's mine, my baby.
I don't own these people.
Exactly.
I don't know these people.
I spent a year researching them at the end of the day.
I never met him.
He's been dead since the 60s.
I don't know him.
mind i don't know these people i don't own these people i don't own their stories exactly yeah i am finding fragments of their life and trying to connect those that is all that was all
I feel very kindred with you with that.
Yeah.
Because everything I do, obviously I don't own.
Yeah, yeah.
It's more because you're interacting with it.
Right, right.
And appreciating it.
You put it so well.
Oh, thank you.
Yeah.
Another broader question.
So you've been here for almost 10 years.
What are some changes in just like the culture or the culture on campus or the student life or anything like that have you seen?
They think there is a housing crisis.
They being the city call station.
That's not true.
This is a lie.
They are
Tearing, you know, building these high-rises that are going to be, you know, $1,600 a month to live with six other people.
And it's very frustrating because who's that helping?
Right.
Not Brian citizens who aren't affiliated with the college.
You're tearing down small businesses owned by ags to build these skyscrapers for kids who probably don't even need to live on Northgate.
Right.
Because part of the reason why you can charge so much in anarchy is because you're by the bars.
So tearing down bars isn't going to help you.
No.
And I'd say, unfortunately, I'm very disconnected to undergrad life.
I mean, that tracks you.
That tracks.
You're out of it.
You're seeing a lot of athleisure on campus.
I'm ready for that to be done.
I'm ready for good start dressing in jeans and industrial clothes as a whole thing.
I haven't seen a lot of online shopping during my TA class that semester, so that's exciting.
It's also early, though.
I don't know.
I think the chat GPT of it all is going to be fascinating.
Yeah.
That's going to be fascinating.
That's something I wanted to bring up, too, is...
because i don't yeah i don't interact with um we were as a library the higher-ups wanted us to see if we could use ai in our daily life yeah a lot of us especially in cushing are against it because that's directly taking our jobs yes
And creating more work.
Yeah.
AI can't pull boxes for you and reel them into the Christian Kelsey reading room.
Yeah, no.
That can happen.
Right.
That can happen now.
Yeah.
No.
So I'm interested, like, how is the student side?
Yeah.
I think in the next five years, we'll see a complete push to online physical paper exams.
I firmly believe that.
Oh, two physical papers?
Yes.
Okay.
I think we're going to completely see.
Back around.
It's going to go completely out of.
Mm-hmm.
Yeah.
I mean, they already did...
I'm 100% for it.
Why are you spending tens of thousands of dollars to plug it into a computer?
Yeah.
If you're a comm major, shouldn't you know how to write officially?
If you're an animator, shouldn't you know the dosage to tranquilize a horse?
Yeah.
What scares me is the...
First of all, no regulation.
And then... No regulation.
Second of all, that...
It just makes stuff up.
They create sources.
Yeah.
They will bring stuff up.
I think a lot of professors are getting smarter with how to combat it.
They are, like, saying you can only use stuff we talked about in the documentary, this reading, things you talked about in the lecture.
You know, we're doing Turnitin, that flags AI.
I would rather...
Experienced this that first round of submissions I had a grade recently.
I was so happy reading an incoherent paragraph.
Because I knew he wrote it.
I'd rather give him line-by-line edits than just give 100 to an encyclopedia.
Right.
That may half it up.
So, I think if you're just honest with kids and showing them, like, well, it makes up sources...
I know when you use it, if you bring up this random thing I specifically did not talk about because I wrote my lecture, you're going to get caught.
I think it's up to the university for being strict when it comes up and not a slap on the wrist.
Yeah, they need to do something.
And you don't want to cheat, steal, or lie.
And I think the university does not have a...
homogenous stance on it either some departments you can use it some you can't and i do think we're being more upfront about it that first syllabus study of like hey in this class you can't use it whatsoever but again i'm not in the headspace of someone who uses it right so i don't know if that's a deal breaker i don't know if that's like well that's fine if i can use it for other classes
I have no idea.
I'm just not in that headspace.
Because I can't do what I need to do with JAPGPT.
I'm creating original research.
Right, yeah.
You're the one... You're creating stuff that's plugged in.
I'm just going to get ripped off.
Yeah, yeah.
Like... Yeah.
That's other than my...
Forget about the environmental.
Forget about the social impact.
Yeah.
The theft is like...
It's the theft.
It's the theft, too.
Not that those things don't matter, because I care about those things.
No, I care about... No, it's...
It's the death of the individual, it's the death of the cognizant, whatever.
It's a long tangent.
It's very interconnected in mass consumerism.
A lot of other words.
I do view people less when I find out these are for everyday life.
I don't care.
Why are you asking me to make you a recipe?